[MUSIC]
Another kind of resource is a layout file.
Layout files specify what
the user interface for
some part of your
application will look like.
And again, these files are written in XML.
Although some tools will allow you
to create the layout visually.
And then those tools will
generate the XML for you.
In fact, Eclipse will do that.
Layout files are typically stored in the
res/layout directory of your application.
And you can access the layout
in Java as R.layout.layout_name.
And you can access that layout in other
resource files as &layout/ layout name.
Now just like string files whose use
depends on your default language,
Android allows you to create multiple
layout files, and then Android can
choose from those files at runtime
based on your device's configuration.
Let's look at an example of that.
So let's look at the main.xml file
that's in the res/layout directory.
This file specifies that
the layout is composed of
something called the RelativeLayout, one
that when we talk about user interfaces.
And inside the relative layout, there's
another element called an edit text.
That's the box that you use for
entering the postal address.
There's also a button, that's
the button that was labeled show map.
Eclipse can also show what it thinks
this will all look like at runtime.
And you can see that by clicking
on the graphical layout tab.
Now once you're there, you can also
click on the individual elements, and
Eclipse will show you more detailed
information about their layout properties.
Map location also has another file,
also called main.xml but
this one is in
the res/layout-land directory.
If map location is running with
a device in landscape mode,
this file is used instead of
the one that we saw before.
Now as you can see, this file uses the
same elements, a relative layout, an edit
text, and a button, but I've changed their
positioning slightly so that the elements
all appear on a single line, which I
think looks better in landscape mode.
And again, you can play around with
Eclipse to get more details about
the layout properties of
each individual element.
Now let's run the application.
The phone on the left is
running in portrait mode, so
it uses the default main.xml file.
The phone on the right, however,
is running in landscape mode.
So it will use the main.xml
file that's in res/layout-land.
And as you can see the elements are
actually laid out differently depending on
the orientation of the device.
Now I've mentioned a few times now
that resources can be accessed in
Java as R.something or another.
Well, to do this Android generates
a class called R, from your application.
And you can then access the fields of
this R class to get to those strings and
layouts and other resources that
you defined in the XML files.
Let's take a look at an,
at an actual R.Java file.
As I've said, this file is generated
by Android so you shouldn't modify it.
You can see that the file
defines the R class and
this R class contains
another class called Layout.
Which has a field called Main.
And that actually gives you a reference or
handle to the main.xml file.
There's also an id class providing
handles to the relative layout,
to the edit text box, and to the button
defined in the main.xml files.
In fact, if you go back and
check the main.xml files now, you'll see
that there are lines that say Android:id.
And that's where these fields and
IDs come from.
And finally, there's a class called
string, which provides handles for
all the strings that
we've been talking about.
The next step in application development
is implementing your Java classes.
And this usually involves
writing at least one activity.
The entry point for
activities is the onCreate method.
So that's where you'll typically
initialize your application.
Let's look at the onCreate
method in a bit more detail.
In onCreate,
you usually do the following four things.
You restore saved application state.
You set the content view,
which tells Android what to display
as the activities user interface.
You initialize specific elements of your
activities user interface, and last,
you attach code to those user interface
elements so that specific actions will
be performed when the users interact
with these user interface elements.
Let's see how these steps
are implemented in MapLocation.
So, let's take a look at
the MapLocation source code.
It's all contained in a file
called MapLocation.java in
the application's source directory.
Now, as you can see this file
implements a class called MapLocation,
which is a subclass of activity.
As an activity it has an onCreate method,
where the application is initialized.
The first step of onCreate is to
call super.onCreate passing saved
instance state as a parameter.
Now this saved instance state is a,
something of type bundle and
it's basically a data structure containing
any information that Android might have
saved from the last time
the activity was running.
We'll talk more about this next time when
we dive deeper into the activity class.
But for now just be aware that
onCreate has to call super.onCreate or
you'll get an error.
Next there's a call to setContentView.
In this case passing in
the reference of the layout file for
this application, R.layout.main.
After that there's some code that acquires
references to individual UI elements in
the layout.
Such as the edit text box, which is
stored in a variable called addrText.
And the button, which is stored
in a variable called button.
As you can see, these references are
acquired by calling activity.findViewById.
And passing in the id
of the desired element.
And finally there's some
code that defines what to
do when the user presses
the show map button.
This code implements the on click
listener interface which has
an onClick method that gets called
whenever the user clicks on this button.
And the code in that onClick method,
first gets any text that the user
has entered in the address box.
Then it process that
text to remove spaces and
put it in a format that
Google Maps understands.
And, then it starts the Google Map app,
Google Maps application passing
in this modified address text.
And again, I'll explain what this code is
doing in more detail in later lessons when
we dive into the workings of
the activity class and the intent class.
And also, just to simplify things,
I've left out any error checking or
verification of the address
string that was input but
of course in production code you
really going to want to do that.
The next step in creating Android
applications is to provide information
that allows Android's build tools to
create the application package, or apk.
And this information is written in
an XML file called AndroidManifest.XML.
The AndroidManifest.XML file contains
a wide variety of packaging information,
including the name of the application, and
a list of the components that
make up that application.
It also includes other information that
we'll discuss later in the course.
Things like the permissions that
are needed to run this application.
The hardware features such as a camera
that this application requires and
the earliest platform version
on which this application runs.
Let's look at the AndroidManifest.XML
file for map location.
The AndroidManifest.XML file is in the top
level directory of the application.
[SOUND] Let's open it now.
[SOUND] Inside,
you see that there's a manifest tag,
telling Android that this file contains
the packaging information that it needs.
There's a lot of other
information in here as well, but
I'll just discuss a few pieces of it.
One element we see here
is the uses SDK element.
This element includes an attribute,
min SDK version that specifies the minimum
API level for this application.
And in this case,
that level is ten which corresponds
to one of the Android 2.3 releases.
This element also includes another
attribute, targetSDKVersion, which
specifies the latest API level against
which this application has been tested.
In this case that's level 17 and
corresponds to a Android 4.2 release.
There's also an application element
that specifies things like the icon for
this application and the label that's
shown in the application's title bar.
Inside the application element, there's
an activity element that lists the one
activity, in this case, map location,
that comprises this application.
And the last step is installing
the application on a device or
emulator in order to test and debug it.
In an earlier lesson,
we saw how to do that in Eclipse.
And you can also do this
from the command line, for
example by issuing
commands to the adb tool.